Register of the Robert Parvin Williams papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Robert Parvin Williams papers
1916-1951
68017
Hoover Institution Archives
8 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize folder (3.5 linear feet)
The papers of Robert Parvin Williams, Brigadier General, U.S. Army, include diaries, memoirs, correspondence, studies, memoranda, photographs, maps, charts, and printed matter relating to the U.S. Army Medical Service in the China-India-Burma Theater during World War II and during the Korean War.
Williams, Robert Parvin
Access
The collection is open for research
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Materials were acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1968.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1891 August 29 Born, Greencastle, Indiana
1912-1913 Intern, Ancon Hospital, Panama Canal Zone
1913 M.D., University of Cincinnati
1913-1915 Cincinnati General Hospital
1915 First Lieutenant, Medical Corps, U.S. Army
1915-1916 Student, Army Medical School
1916-1917 Adjutant, Camp Hospital, Mexican border, Douglas, Arizona
1917-1918 Assistant Divisional Surgeon
1918 Organizer and Commander, General Hospital No. 34, East Norfolk, Massachusetts
1927 Honor graduate, Medical Field Service School
1928-1930 Student, Command and General Staff School
1934-1935 Army War College
1935 Chemical Warfare School
1935-1939 Instructor, Infantry School, Fort Benning, Georgia
1939-1940 Director, training, Medical Field Service School, Carlisle Barracks, Pennsylvania
1940 Commanding officer, First Regiment, march from Pennsylvania to California
1942 February 5 Member, General Joseph Stilwell's military mission to China and Burma
1942 May Surgeon, General Stilwell's column, retreat from Burma to India
1944-1945 Chief surgeon, General Dan I. Sultan, India-Burma theater
1945 July-1949 Army surgeon, Fourth Army
1949 September-November Special assistant to surgeon general
1949 Promoted through grades to Brigadier General
1967 November 20 Died
Scope and Content of Collection
The papers of Robert Parvin Williams, Brigadier General, U.S. Army, include diaries, memoirs, correspondence, studies, memoranda, photographs, maps, charts, and printed matter relating to the U.S. Army Medical Service in the China-India-Burma Theater during World War II and during the Korean War.
The Biographical File, in addition to Williams' curriculum vitae and citations, offers an example of his skills as a writer and a speaker. But of more interest to the researchers might be his diaries, divided in sections in chronological order, recording announcements of citations, daily events and schedules, his itineraries, and descriptions of performance of his duties in the context of the prevalent military situation of 1941 to 1945.
The bulk of the materials in the collection relate to the services provided by the medical units of different army divisions within the framework of the United States Army operations in various parts of the world. All of these documents are included in the United States Army File. The materials are listed in chronological order under the names of the army units with a description of physical forms. Williams' work in the China-Burma-India theater along with General Joseph Stilwell deserves a particular mention.
The series of Photographs is a visual record of army operations involving machinery, weapons, and individuals. Some photographic prints are attached to the materials they illustrate, and they have been left in the United States Army File where noted. Loose prints, including oversize prints, are generally listed in chronological order with information about dates and the names of photographers whenever available. Loose prints found in the folders have been left in place, as they might be better understood if considered in the context of the materials in the folder.
Related Material
Joseph W. Stilwell papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Frank Dorn papers, Hoover Institution Archives
Raymond A. Wheeler papers, Hoover Institution Archives
United States. Army Medical Service.; United States. Army--Officers.; United States—Armed Forces.; China.; Korean War, 1950-1953.; World War, 1939-1945--Campaigns--Burma.; World War, 1939-1945--China.; World War, 1939-1945--Medical care.; World War, 1939-1945.
- Biographical File, 1940-1951 (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Includes a curriculum vitae, citations, diary, index to Williams' personal correspondence, and writings and speeches by him and by others, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - Biographical information up to 1951 March 9, circa 1951 (Box-folder 1: 1)
  - Citations, undated (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Diary, 1941-1945 (Box-folder 1: 3)
  - Index to personal correspondence
    - 1948 January 2 – August 10 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - 1949 January 3 – July 11 (Box-folder 1: 5)
  - Notes, 1940 April 27 (Box-folder 1: 6)
  - Writings and speeches
    - "The New Regimental Medical Detachment," an Infantry School teaching, Military Surgeon, 1940 January (Box-folder 1: 7)
    - "One Man's CBI: A Different Kind of War,", 1942
      - Introduction, "The Hike" (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - Part I – India (Box-folder 1: 9)
        Includes photographs.
      - Part II - China (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - Part III – Burma (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Speech, members of the graduating class, Army Specialized Training Program, Brooke Army Medical Center, Fort Sam Houston, Texas, 1947 September 19 (Box-folder 1: 12)
    - "Medical Participation in Exercise Seminole," with Arin F. Robinson, Military Surgeon, 1948 December (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
      Includes related correspondence, 1947 October 10 – 1949 April 11, one undated letter, one telegram, and photographic prints.
  - Writings by others
    - T. E. Darby and Paul E. Zuver, 1940 January (Box-folder 1: 15)
    - Francis P. Kintz and John Edgar, 1950 January-March (Box-folder 1: 16)
    - Amos R. Koontz, 1950 December (Box-folder 1: 17)
    - James B. Mason and Charles H. Beasley, 1950 December (Box-folder 1: 18)
    - Spurgeon H. Neel, Jr., 1950 November, 1951 February (Box-folder 1: 19-20)
    - James H. Stone, military, 1949 March, October (Box-folder 1: 21-22)
- United States Army File, 1916–1951 (Boxes 1-7)
  Relates to Army War College instruction, the role of medical service units in the context of the United States Army operations in general, performance of various army units and training facilities, and the conduct of the war based on situations in different geographical areas.
  - Army War College
    - Conduct of War course, part II, Analytical Studies, undated (Box-folder 1: 23)
    - Map, Chickamauga and Tullahoma campaigns, undated (Box-folder 1: 24)
    - Conduct of War course, map problem I, undated (Box-folder 1: 25)
    - G-1 to G-4 courses, undated (Box-folder 1: 26)
    - G-2 course, undated (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Special map no. 5, 1930 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - War Plans course, volume I, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 2: 3)
      Includes a map of Bureau of Coast and Geodetic Survey, Central Luzon, Philippine Islands, 1931.
    - Gettysburg-Richmond map, 1932 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - General, Fort Humphreys, 1934 March 26 – 1935 June 25 (Box-folder 2: 5)
    - G-3 course, 1934 September 28 – October 4 (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - G-1 course, 1934 October 12 – December 19 (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - G-4 course, 1934 November 12-28 (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Conduct of War course, part I, Analytical Studies, lectures, 1935 January – February 4 (Box-folder 2: 9)
    - War Plans course, volume I (a) – Presentation of "Overseas Possession" by Robert Williams, study no. 3, Philippine Islands, 1935 March 1 (Box-folder 2: 10)
    - War Plans course, volume III, 1935 April 1-5 (Box-folder 2: 11)
    - Preparation for War course, part II, 1935 April 18 – May 1 (Box-folder 2: 12)
      Individual general staff memoranda, medical service of the Cavalry Division, 1935 June 3.
    - Conduct of War course, no. 20, lectures delivered by Fox Connor, William D. Connor, D. E. Nolan, and Chas F. B. Price, Army War College, Fort Humphreys, Washington, D.C., 1935 May 10 – June 6 (Box-folder 2: 13)
    - Conduct of War course, part II, no. 23, Field Exercise, Army War College, Fort Humphreys, Washington, D.C., 1935 June 10-12 (Box-folder 2: 14)
      Includes notes and related materials.
    - Clippings, 1935 June 19-20 (Box-folder 2: 15)
    - Conduct of War course, second map problem period, 1935 June-July (Box-folder 2: 16)
  - Medical Field Service
    - General, undated (Box-folder 3: 1)
      Relates to combat principles, equipment and supplies, functions, and training drills.
    - Department of Training, Industrial Mobilization and Procurement Planning report, undated (Box-folder 3: 2)
    - Manual for the Medical Department, 1916 (Box-folder 3: 3)
      Corrected to June 15, 1918.
    - Medical service in a modern Cavalry Division, 1930 October-November (Box-folder 3: 4)
      Memoranda and report.
    - Brochures, 1934-1936, undated (Box-folder 3: 5)
    - Tactical Employment of the Medical Service (tentative) C&GSS report, 1938 (Box-folder 3: 6)
    - Eighth Army maps, 1940 (Box-folder 3: 7)
    - First Medical Squadron
      - 1927 October 13 – 1935 December 9, undated (Box-folder 3: 8)
        Clipping, correspondence, memoranda, notes, and reports.
      - 1929 September 8 – 1932 March 23 (Box-folder 3: 9)
        Correspondence with Condon C. McCormack.
      - 1929 – 1932 July 18, undated (Box-folder 3: 10)
        Includes chart for evacuation of casualties, list of personnel, notes, and printed matter.
      - 1929 November 1 – 1933 September 28, undated (Box-folder 3: 11)
        Correspondence with Edgar King.
      - 1930 April 7 – 1933 September 20, undated (Box-folder 3: 12)
        Correspondence, memoranda, and notes.
      - 1931 January 6 – 1940 March 22 (Box-folder 3: 13)
        Memoranda and notes.
      - 1932 January 19 – August 4, undated (Box-folder 3: 14)
        List of supplies, notes, proceedings of conference, and summary of intelligence records.
      - 1932 June 27, undated (Box-folder 3: 15)
        Letter, photographic prints, and illustrations.
      - 1933 December 4, undated (Box-folder 3: 16)
        Letter and photographic prints.
      - 1940 April – September 3 (Box-folder 4: 1)
        Chart, correspondence, memoranda, press release, report, and telegram.
      - Miscellany, 1930-1933, undated (Box-folder 4: 2)
        Includes related materials, some photographic prints with illustrations, and Christmas programs.
    - Fourth Army
      - 1940 April 13 – May 2 (Box-folder 4: 3)
        Instructions.
      - 1947 August 31 – 1949 December (Box-folder 4: 4)
        Brochure, list of numbered hospitals as of 1945 May 31, memoranda, and photographic prints.
      - 1947 September 8 – 1948 January 30, undated (Box-folder 4: 5)
        Correspondence, list of personnel, and report of the General Board, United States Forces, European Theater.
      - 1947 October 15 – 1949 February, undated (Box-folder 4: 6)
        Memoranda, notes, report, and telegrams.
      - 1948 January 26 – April 2 (Box-folder 4: 7)
        Correspondence, list, memoranda, and miscellany.
      - 1948 January 29 – February 26 (Box-folder 4: 8)
        Correspondence and memoranda.
      - 1948 March 29 – April 30 (Box-folder 4: 9)
        Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials.
      - 1948 May 3 - June 4 (Box-folder 4: 10)
        Correspondence.
      - 1948 June 2–30 (Box-folder 4: 11)
      - 1948 July 2 – August 10 (Box-folder 4: 12)
      - 1948 – 1949 January 31 (Box-folder 4: 13)
        Correspondence, memoranda, record of telephone conversation, and miscellany.
      - 1949 January 31 – February 28 (Box-folder 4: 14)
      - 1949 February 28 – March 31 (Box-folder 4: 15)
      - 1949 April 4–20 (Box-folder 4: 16)
        Correspondence, memoranda, and miscellany.
      - 1949 May 2–31 (Box-folder 4: 17)
        Correspondence, memoranda, and related materials
      - 1949 June 1–30, undated (Box-folder 4: 18)
        Correspondence, memoranda, and note.
      - 1949 June 27 – July 11 (Box-folder 4: 19)
    - Infantry School, 1938-1939
      - General
        - 1925 January – 1939 March 7 (Box-folder 5: 1)
          Course material, map, and memoranda.
        - 1939 February 20 – June 1 (Box-folder 5: 2)
          Course and test materials and map.
        - Conference, part I, Legal Aspects, section I, Continental United States, undated (Box-folder 5: 3)
      - Maneuvers, sections I-V, 1939 June 2-9 (Box-folder 5: 4-6)
      - Mimeographed instructional matter, 1938-1939
        - Volumes I-II (Box-folder 5: 7-8)
        - Volumes III-V (Box-folder 6: 1-3)
    - Ninth Corps, 1940 May 9 – 1941 October 24 (Box-folder 6: 4)
      Correspondence, medical organizational records, and memoranda.
    - Seventh Infantry Division, 1950 October 27 – 1951 March 11 (Box-folder 6: 5)
      Memoranda.
    - Subject file
      - China-Burma-India Theater (CBI), 1942 May 30 - 1945 October 5, undated (Box-folder 6: 6)
        Clipping, diary, graphs, list of personnel, maps, memoranda, military circulars, printed matter, and related materials.
      - Civilian Conservation Corps (CCC), Arizona, 1932 – 1934 April, undated (Box-folder 6: 7)
        Booklet, correspondence, journal, memoranda, notes, photographic prints, and printed matter.
      - Far East Command, 1950 October 17 – 1951 February 1, undated (Box-folder 6: 8)
        Bulletin, list of personnel, medical information, memoranda, note, and related materials.
      - Japan, Nara Station Hospital, 1951 March 17 – April 5, undated (Box-folder 7: 1)
        Includes information booklet, operational data, memoranda, notes, physical reconditioning program, and sketches.
      - Korea, Eighth Army
        - General, 1951 March 1 – April 30, undated (Box-folder 7: 2)
          Agenda for Medical Policy Council, list of medical service personnel and patients, notes, operational data from surgeon general's office, and related materials.
        - Maps, regions of Korea, 1951 March 19, undated (Box-folder 7: 3)
          Includes Inchon, Chunghon, and Samchok; and I Corps medical installations.
        - Report, Robert Williams' trip to Korea, 1951 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - Mountain Stretchers, 1943 January 22, undated (Box-folder 7: 5)
        Includes bibliography and photographic prints with illustrations.
    - Third Army, 1940 January 17 – May 15, undated (Box-folder 7: 6)
      Maneuvers. Includes maps and photographic prints.
    - War Department
      - 1929 September 8 – 1933 June 27, undated (Box-folder 7: 7)
        Correspondence with Garfield L. McKinney.
      - 1930 June 2 – 1933 September 21 (Box-folder 7: 8)
        Correspondence with T. E. Darby. Includes memoranda.
      - 1932 August 16 – 1933 July 7 (Box-folder 7: 9)
        Correspondence with Fred?
      - 1937 January – 1950 October 12 (Box-folder 7: 10)
        Medical instructors bulletin and memoranda.
      - 1937 June 15 – 1940 September 10, undated (Box-folder 7: 11)
        Memoranda, report of physical examination of enlisted men on induction, and special orders.
      - 1939 (Box-folder 7: 12)
        Protective Mobilization Plan, including change No. 3, 1940 January 16.
      - 1940 May 25 – July 8, undated (Box-folder 7: 13)
        Chart, correspondence, memoranda, and notes.
    - Miscellany
      - "The Cacolet,", undated (Box-folder 7: 14)
        Some photographic prints attached to the materials.
      - Inspection records, 1951 March 2 – October 3 (Box-folder 7: 15)
        Clippings, correspondence, memoranda, and notes.
      - "The Story of a Small Campaign: The Medical Arrangements During the Burma Rebellion, 1931," Major General J. W. West, Journal of the Royal Army Medical Corps, 1933 June (Box-folder 7: 16)
      - Sketches from the Medical Department Equipment Laboratory, undated (Box-folder 7: 17)
- Photographs, 1927–1950, undated (Map case, Box 8)
  277 photographic prints, including 2 oversize prints of Army officials and 27 negatives, reflecting army operations with machinery and individuals.
  - 2 oversize group photographic prints of army officials, undated (Map case)
  - 43 prints, Cavalry Division, and 5 prints depicting army vehicles, undated (Box-folder 8: 1)
  - 18 prints depicting army operations, modes of transport, and personnel, undated (Box-folder 8: 2)
  - 4 prints and 2 negatives taken by Johnny McKee depicting D-Day on the Florida Gulf coast objective area, undated (Box-folder 8: 3)
  - 26 prints depicting the sea, ships with numbers, military vehicles, land transports, and soldiers (including wounded ones), undated (Box-folder 8: 4)
  - 12 prints depicting soldiers with horses in open fields or by a mountain, Fort Bliss, Texas, undated (Box-folder 8: 5)
  - 1 print depicting 4 soldiers (their names are on the other side of the print) standing in front of a building, 1927 August (Box-folder 8: 6)
  - 5 prints (taken by Don Thompson?) depicting soldiers with horses engaged in various activities, circa 1931 (Box-folder 8: 7)
  - 86 prints, including some from Cavalry Division, depicting soldiers involved in various activities, 1932 (Box-folder 8: 8)
  - 12 prints depicting soldiers playing and a building, Army War College, 1934-1935 (Box-folder 8: 9)
  - 2 prints of a number of people (with their names listed) belonging to different medical groups, Fourth Corps, 1940 (Box-folder 8: 10)
  - 29 prints depicting China-Burma-India sector, including the retreat from Burma to India with a note from Joseph Stilwell about Robert Williams' contribution and award of the Purple Heart to Joseph Stilwell, 1942 (Box-folder 8: 11)
    Includes description of the prints on the other side.
  - 6 prints taken by John McKee depicting soldiers of the Second Armored Division, 1947 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - 25 negatives and 2 miniature films returned by the Fourth Army with a request for developing for the purpose of using them in an article, 1948 (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - 1 print depicting a soldier receiving medical care during the Korean conflict, 1950 (Box-folder 8: 14)
- Declassified U.S. Government Records, 1944 (Box 7)
  Formerly security-classified records of the U.S. government, released in full or in part. Arranged chronologically by date of release by Hoover, thereunder chronologically by date of creation.
  - 2016 February release of records, 1944 September 2 (Box-folder 7: 18)
    [China-Burma-India] Theater Map indicating sectional boundaries and their dates of establishment. Produced by the Office of the Chief Engineer, U.S. Air Force.